<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Around the world in 80 days</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/</link><description>Blog for an 80 day coding and exercise experiment.</description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 19:12:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Kate and Henry's Hacking night at Henry's</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/kate-and-henrys-hacking-night-at-henrys.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="what"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in computing, hardware, software, art, music,
culture then come along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free and open software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="when"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;When&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday's from beer O'clock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First event: Tuesday 20th October 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be there from 6pm Bermuda time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="where"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry VII's pub and restaurant in Southampton Bermuda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are four or less will probably just grab a table in the bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are more I've been offered the room in the back of the sushi
restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="why"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let other's know what you are up to, share ideas, code, music, art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="who"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anybody and everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you are Henry, Henri, Enrique,
Kate, Kathryn or Katrina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Has gone back to Wales, but we can always work on a Henry
simulator, plus there are pleny of Henry pictures on the walls.
Might not be a wise idea.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things didn't work out too well for Henry's Kates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There might be hacking, but the only thing being executed will be
code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="agenda"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Agenda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are volunteers to present ideas, let me know and I will
advertise more widely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="visitors"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Visitors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are visiting the island do come along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to know how to get to Henry's, number 7 bus will get you
there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From town any number 7, just tell the driver you are going to Henry's
or Gibb's Hill Lighthouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to climb the lighthouse, note that it closes at 4pm, but
it is always a good place to watch the sunset from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>free software</category><category>fun</category><category>meetup</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/kate-and-henrys-hacking-night-at-henrys.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 18:31:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hurricane Joaquin</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/hurricane-joaquin.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hurricane Joaquim is now category 4 and expected to strengthen some
more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been over the Bahamas for a long time now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bermudaweather.wordpress.com/"&gt;Michael Johnston&lt;/a&gt;'s weather blog is a wonderful, Bermuda centric
weather blog and a good resource to check for those in Bermuda
wondering if Joaquin is heading this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael is currently studying meteorology at Penn State.  He worked at
the Bermuda weather service this summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="uncertainty-in-paths"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Uncertainty in paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been consdierable disagreement across models over what track
this storm will take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather systems are complex at present.  The models are coming
into better agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In situations like this it would be very useful to have more
information on the likely intensity given each path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Hurricane Centre discussion is always helpful.  It feels
like the forecasts are getting better at getting the intensity right,
given the right track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track tends to be driven by larger systems whose interaction is
hard to predict.  But often, given the direction the hurricane travels
we can learn a bit about how those systems will evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that open and free software combined, with open scientific
collaboration, can help communities better prepare for these events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="direction-of-change-in-model-predictions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Direction of change in model predictions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way the model predictions move can be informative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the models may have been leaning more in that direction, all of
them would likely have assigned some probability to the general
direcion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seems to be some inertia in the models, so sometimes as they
shift the direction of the forecast, the next update also moves a
little in that direction: when the forecasts are changing, more change
is often more likely, it indicates that the driving features are
changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="climate-change"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Climate Change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it indicates there is a new factor in play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate change is increasing occurrences of unusual weather.  Regions
are experiencing conditions at the extremes of what they have
experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases these are conditions that the region is poorly adapted
to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The models will also be experiencing conditions outside the area where
they have been callibrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will provide good data and new insigts to improve them for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bermuda"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bermuda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first anniversary of Fay and Gonzalo is fast approaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now Joaquin is moving very slowly, battering Caribbean islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest forecasts have it well west of Bermuda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track should become more certain over then next 24 hours or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Latest 11,00pm EDT October 1, 2015 discussion has this paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The forecast models continue to indicate a track farther away
from the United States east coast and the threat of direct impacts
from Joaquin in the Carolinas and mid-Atlantic states appears to be
decreasing.  However, the threat of impacts in Bermuda has increased
and a Tropical Storm or Hurricane Watch could be required for that
island on Friday.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be good to have more info on the likely intensity should it
take a path close to Bermuda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There still appears to be a fair bit of uncertainty about the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hurricane</category><category>Joaquin</category><category>weather</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/hurricane-joaquin.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 02:18:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Computing Hermeneutics: let the source be with you.</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/computing-hermeneutics.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Someone asked me recently to explain the difference between coding and
programmes, using a suitable analogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not good at short answers, so here is a longer one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between the source code and the programme has changed
dramatically over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, the problem boils down to humans specifying what a
computer should do.   We speak different languages, our input/ouput
devices work differently and our central processing units are
fundamentally different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, computer programming is a bit like writing a document for
someone to read, but that someone does not speak your language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes everything you say literally and has no capacity to "do what
I mean, not what I say".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They can do certain tasks incredibly quickly, like the gifted child
that can amaze you with music, maths or art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coding is the process of writing the instructions for the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="source-code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Source Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source code is what the computer programmer creates.  It is the
human readable version of the computer instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="programme"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Programme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The human readable instructions generally need to be converted into
another form for the computer to understand.  The resulting version is
known as the programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="electro-mechanical-computing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Electro-Mechanical computing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computers at dawn of modern computing were electro-mechanical
devices such as the Bombes, designed by Alan Turing to crack the
Enigma codes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Programming&lt;/em&gt; the Bombes involved manyally setting dials and using
wires to enter settings on plug boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these devices, the source code and the programme were essentially
the same thing: the physical settings of the wheels, dials and
plug-board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, humans learned to speak the same language as the computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="machine-code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Machine Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first fully electronic computers were programmed with machine
code, essentially just a stream of numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each operation the computer could do had a numeric code.  Memory
locations were expressed as numbers as were the input values for
calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the human programmers were having to learn the language the
computer actually understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was some help for humans, the machine code might be written in
hexadecimal, not the binary that the computer can actually store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="assembly-language"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Assembly Language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this was incredibly time consuming.  Skilled machine code
programmers were a rare breed.  Computers were also quite rare at this
time, so there were generally enough programmers to go round and they
were too busy writing machine code to worry about creating and
learning new languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, getting data into and out of these early computers was a
challenge in itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon punched cards and computer tape took over these roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assembly languages were developed.  These languages used names such as
&lt;em&gt;add&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;mul&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mov&lt;/em&gt; to represent the numeric operations the
computer actually understands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special programmes, called &lt;em&gt;assemblers&lt;/em&gt; were used to translate from
this assembly language that was easier for humans to produce to the
machine language that the computers understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task of programming was still very challenging, but by now the
version of the code that the computer understood and was able to use
was different to that the programmer writes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers and programmers were still pretty rare species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="high-level-languages"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;High level languages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once there were assembly languages it was a natural progression to
higher level languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These languages had higher level constructs that &lt;em&gt;compilers&lt;/em&gt; could
translate into assembly language and in turn the &lt;em&gt;assembler&lt;/em&gt; could
turn into machine code that computers could run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This separation later proved invaluable, since different models of
computer had different instruction sets and required different
assembler languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bootstrapping"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bootstrapping&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing a compiler for a new language is a challenging task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is common practice to write the compiler in the language that it is
intended to compile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this creates a &lt;em&gt;chicken and egg&lt;/em&gt; situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you compile your compiler, if it is written in a new language?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of solutions to this problem that have been used,
but all boil down to using some other compiler to pull you up by your
boot straps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often these tools implement a subset of the language, but can be used
to compile the whole compiler including the additional features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have got this far, you can use your newly compiled compiler
to compile itself.   The language has become &lt;em&gt;self-hosting&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="virtual-machines"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Virtual Machines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early computers were extremely slow compared to today's
computers.  Compilers would be written for each specific architecture
in order to take full advantage of the computer's capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As computers became faster it became feasible to write &lt;em&gt;virtual
machines&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These virtual machines would implement a general purpose instruction
set.  To actually run virtual machine code on a specific computer
architecture it is necessary to  create an implementation of that
virtual machine on the specific hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic of virtual machines is that it separates the problem of
making a particular machine run fast from the problem of specifying
what you want it to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, virtual machines promised: &lt;em&gt;write once, run everywhere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java and .NET are good examples of virtual machine technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="interpreted-languages"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interpreted languages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compiling code can be time consuming.  The higher level a language is
the more work the computer has to do to translate the language into
something it can run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good compilers will also attempt to optimise code, allowing the
programmer to specify what the computer should do, but letting the
compiler figure out an efficient way to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the programmer can help the compiler by using algorithms
and constructs that they know the compiler will implement
efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As computers became faster it became possible to do compilation of
code on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programmers using compiled languages go through a cycle of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;writing code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compiling the code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;running the code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;figuring out why it did not do what they expected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rinse and repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compile stage can be time consuming and interrupts a programmers
train of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interpretted languages typically also make use of a virtual machine.
They compile the code into virtual machine byte codes that can then be
executed directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perl and Python are examples of interpretted languages.  I remember
when I first discovered Perl, my productivity went up dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="literate-programming"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Literate Programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer programmes can (and in my view should) be considered as works
of literature: written works to communicate not just with computers
but also with other computer programmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that most programmers spend the vast majority of time
reading, maintaining and developing existing code, rather than writing
new code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a strong incentive for programmers to write clear code that
is easy for others to follow: the person most likely to read your code
is yourself.  Maybe six hours later, six days, six months or even six
years in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great languages not only make it easier to express what you want the
computer to do but also make it easier to write readable code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly great languages make it harder to write code that looks like it
does one thing, but really does something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, they allow some level of ambiguity.  They work on
many levels, lika all great literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a sort algorithm that can sort anything, just so long as
you tell it how to compare objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="open-source"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Open Source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source software is software that makes the source code available,
not just the executable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is this important?  Well if you want to understand what the
software is doing, the best way to do that is to have the work of
literature that the programmers creating the programme used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source software makes these works of literature available to
you.  It is like having the actual draft for a book.  Not only do you
get the story, but you get the author's notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the programmer is using version control, you get the whole history
of the book.  All the thoughts, all the experiments that were tried,
the failures and the successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the source code, you are missing much of the plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="free-software"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Free Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free software takes this one step further.  Not only does it give you
the work of literature, but it gives you the freedom to examine it, to
change it, to write your own story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gives you the freedom to experiment and explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="disassembly"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Disassembly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disassembly is the reverse of what an &lt;em&gt;assembler&lt;/em&gt; does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissassemblers take code that a computer understands and turn it into
code a human can understand better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of them are remarkably good and produce code that an experienced
programmer can understand well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, python bytecodes can be disassembled into very readable
python code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="code-obfustification"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Code obfustification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some software is put through an &lt;em&gt;obfustification&lt;/em&gt; process before it is
released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meaningful function and variable names that the programmer used
are replaced with arbitrary labels.  Comments are removed from the
code.  In short, the goal is to make it hard to discover how the
programme actually works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the code can always be disassembled and with enough
patience and time it is possible to discover how it actually works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, check the license agreement before you do this, much closed
source software explicitly forbids disassembly in the license
agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="project-jypyter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Jypyter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays there are many, many computer languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has created a problem for computer programmers: they are not all
speaking the same language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is needed is some sort of Bablefish that allows programmers and
programmes to communicate with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Jupyter is one such Bablefish.  It supports over 50 languages
and allows seamless interaction between those languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="it-is-all-about-language-and-communication"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It is all about language and communication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software is all about communication.  If you are a computer, machine
code is your friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are human, &lt;em&gt;Use the source, Luke.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if the source is not available, maybe you need to read a different book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/computing-hermeneutics.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 13:15:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Mountains, Valleys and Bridges</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/mountains-valleys-and-bridges.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="hill-climbing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hill Climbing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up close to the hills of the Peak District in Derbyshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highest point of the Peak District is the summit of Kinder Scout.
This is also the first hill along the Pennine Way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most times I have climbed it via Grindsbrook.  It is steep in places
and follows alongside a small river and stream.  This used to be the
Pennine Way route, but now the official route takes you up the
gentler, but no less strenuous, Jacob's Ladder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not even sure if I have ever made it to the highest point on
Kinder Scout.  The summit is more of a plateau, a strange landscape of
tiny streams running along little valleys cut into the peat the covers
the summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most times I have been there it has been covered in cloud, navigating
with the help of a compass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on a clear day you can walk to the spectacular Kinder Downfall and
see all the way to Manchester and even beyond to the mountains of
Snowdonia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the UK, hills become mountains if they are 3000 feet or higher.
Snowdonia has mountains, the Peak District has hills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="false-summits"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;False summits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some hills I have climbed tease you with false summits.   You think
you are nearing the top, and then as you clamber over rocks, behind
what you thought was the summit, the route continues, onward and
upward.  Some hills have many false summits, each more enticing than
the last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="summits"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reaching a summit is always a highlight.  Stood on the highest point
in the area and, weather permitting there will be uninterrupted views
all around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="following-a-ridge"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Following a Ridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having toiled to climb a hill you will rightly be satisfied with the
view you have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when you look across the land there is a spectactular
hill, dwarfing the one you have just climbed.  You can only imagine
how the view might look from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often the new summit is easily accessible from where you are, by
following a ridge that connects to the peak you have just climbed.  A
small descent and a longer climb may be all that is needed to reach a
new high-point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ridge acts like a natural bridge between two summits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bridging-the-valley"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bridging the valley&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes there is no such bridge.  Curiosity might drive you to
attempt the larger peak in the distance, but descending into the
valley after all that hard work climbing, just to climb another hill,
can be a daunting task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be a river in the valley bottom, difficult to cross and
requiring a detour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bridges across valleys connect those either side.  They can be
difficult to build.  Without people either side willing to work
together it may not be possible to cross the divide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crossing a new bridge requires courage too.  There are rope walkways
across plunging gorges that I for one do not have the courage to
cross, let alone be the first to try out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first across are generally the bridge builders, often crossing
before the bridge is complete, fixing it along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Millennium Bridge across the Thames in London.  When people
started to walk across the bridge, the rhythm of their steps caused it
to resonate and wobble.  It was closed for months for modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soldiers always break out of step when marching across a bridge, for a
similar reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who build bridges have courage and vision, leading the way to a
new mountain with a more spectacular view, or uniting communities
previously separated by a plunging ravine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="going-the-long-way-round"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Going the long way round&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often there is no bridge, the valley may be too wide or deep, or just
not enough people wanting to cross to justify a high-level crossing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you can rest at the summit, admire the view and be content with
your achievements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you may be intrigued by the mountain you have seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Descending into the valley you may get that sinking feeling, as you
lose all that height that took so much work to gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The valley bottom may have a bubbling river where you can drink,
perhaps catch a fish and regroup for the climb ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once, refreshed the long climb starts.  As you climb you can gauge
progress by looking across to the hill on which you once stood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point you will draw level with the summit and once again be
able to see the view beyond the hill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be daunted, recalling how much taller this mountain is, how
much more you have to climb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But every step takes you higher than you were before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bridges</category><category>hill climbing</category><category>hills</category><category>mountains</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/mountains-valleys-and-bridges.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 12:33:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Magic Roundabouts and Geese</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/magic-roundabouts-and-geese.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Growing up as children we would watch The Magic Roundabout on the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a five minute children's program with a carousel, Zebedee,
Dougal the dog and Dylan the rabbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each episode ended with Zebedee saying, "Time for bed", before
springing off, literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we got older we might watch a bit of the news that followed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="roundabouts-around-the-world"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Roundabouts around the world&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the world, traffic rules vary quite a bit.  Here are some
examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="france"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;France&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In France roundabouts used to be much less common than in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early traffic rule was essentially, "priorite a la droite".  This
rule dated back to horses and carriages and mostly they could see each
other coming for a good way, it was simple to slow down and give way
to those from one side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key rule, is which side of the road to drive on.  The French,
like most of continental Europe, drive on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looked at from above, the French go anti-clockwise around
roundabouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when they arrive at one, those already on the roundabout give way
to new arrivals, coming from the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works well with light traffic.  With heavy draffic, things can
fall apart: once the roundabout is full of cars nobody can go
anywhere, although if you are just taking the first right then you'll
probably be ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="arc-de-triomphe"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Arc de Triomphe&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is more like The Magic Roundabout.  I have no idea what the
rules are.   Rumour has it that insurance companies exclude any
accident that happens here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="british-isles"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;British Isles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here they drive on the left and go clockwise round roundabouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You give way to those already on the roundabout.  Those already on can
keep going, those arriving have to wait for it to be safe to enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, like the French you are giving way to those on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, it can work well it depends on the traffic volume and pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="swindon"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Swindon&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swindon actually has a Magic Roundabout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a crazy construction of five roundabouts with another roundabout
inside them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UK rules apply, so once you get on the thing it is like a
roller-coaster, just go with the flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the accidents happen, people are usually moving pretty slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="north-america"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;North America&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roundabouts used to be far less common in North America.  Four-way
stops are the order of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You arrive at the junction and stop.  If no-one else is there then you
can proceed, others arriving after you should give way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this can lead to the &lt;em&gt;Canadian stand-off&lt;/em&gt;.   You arrive at a
roundabout just as someone else arrives.  There then follows an
elaborate dance where you both just sit there waiting for the other to
go first, often accompanied by hand-gestures.   Dead-lock is not
uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ottawa"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Ottawa&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a roundabout near the Experimental Farm that itself seems to
be a wonderful experiment in mixing British and French roundabout
rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the day it was probably a four way stop, a simple cross-roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's pretend there is a north-south (NS) road crossing east-west (EW)
and the NS is the bigger road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are travelling NS or SN, you can pretent your are French and
drive straight on to the roundabout.  Those coming from an EW
direction will give way to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are turning left, then you will have to give way to traffic
entering on the NS road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you arrive on the EW road you have to give way to traffic
already on the roundabout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is a complicated mixture of giving way to the left or right
depending on where you are on the roundabout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="going-backwards-round-the-magic-roundabout"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Going backwards round the magic roundabout&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;* please don't try this *&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traffic arriving from east (or west) could do a Pierre Trudeau, behind
the Queen pirouette, turning 180 degrees to enter the roundabout
backwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, the &lt;em&gt;give way to traffic on your right&lt;/em&gt; rule ensures the
traffic that you need to giver way to is always coming from your right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once on the roundabout another pirouette should be done, having done
this, again give way to traffic entering from the North/South road,
which is again on your right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also ensures if you exit on this route you are facing the right
way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If continuing around the roundabout, another pirouette should be
performed after passing the north/south road.  Hence, you will again
be going backwards on the magic roundabout.   With your right side to
the centre of the roundabout there is no need to give way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was much younger my mother one night announced she felt a
little typsy.  As a curious child I asked what that was like.  She
said, "it is like I am going backwards on the magic roundabout".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I said, don't try this on the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="johnny-barnes"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Johnny Barnes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hamilton, Bermuda there are several roundabouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is one special one.  It is known as The Johnny Barnes
roundabout and has its own magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is indeed magic.  Every weekday, between 5am and 10am you will see
Johnny Barnes.  He has been waving to traffic and dispensing love
at the roundabout since retiring from the Bus company.  He is now in
his 90's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bermuda has its own road rules.  Mostly following the British.  But
the horn only really gets used to say &lt;em&gt;hi&lt;/em&gt; to friends and cousins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you see a friend trying to get out of a small side road you might
well follow the "priorite a la droite" rule and wave for them to go
ahead of you, even though you have right of way.  The roads are
narrow, the speed limit is 20 mph and a little give and take makes it
a better place for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you are new to the island, watch out for vehicles stopping to let
people out of tiny driveways and side roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-about-the-geese"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What about the geese?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week the Mighty Blades played Swindon.  Those brave fans that
made the journey down to Swindon went there knowing they would have to
negotiate the Magic Roundabout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being Blades fans, they were probably expecting the worst and a heavy
defeat.  I believe all the fans got through the roundabout unscathed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the game, well the new manager, Nigel Adkins, played a
motivational video before the game.  Google "geese sufc" and you
should find it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It explains how geese are able to travel 70% further by flying in a V
formation.  How one goose will lead and when tired drop back into the
formation and let another take the lead.d&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a goose is tiring and struggling, two other strong geese will drop
down to the ocean with the struggler and stay with it until it either
dies or makes a recovery.  They will then fly together to rejoin the
flock, or tag onto another flock following behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="magic-roundabouts-and-mother-geese"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Magic Roundabouts and Mother Geese&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, my mum was my Magic Roundabout.  She would watch
the world circling around her and find ways to change the paths of
those that needed to be on a different path, or gently put together
those that would benefit from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now have another Magic Roundabout in my life.  Mum's are magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bermuda</category><category>blades</category><category>france</category><category>ottawa</category><category>roundabouts</category><category>sufc</category><category>swindon</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/magic-roundabouts-and-geese.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 14:54:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Census Survey</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/census-survey.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="introduction"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bermuda Government, Department of Statistics has put out a Request
for Proposal (RFP) for a &lt;em&gt;web-based solution to support on-line
census&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some thoughts on how Free Software could form the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The census raises many complex issues of privacy, accessibility and
access to information.  In short, is has all the features of a
typical software project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="free-software-solution"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Free Software Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most, if not all, of the pieces required to build this system already
exist as free software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This software is free in the sense that it gives you freedom.  Freedom
to examine the software, freedom to look how it works, freedom to
change it as you wish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freedom to pass the software on to others should you wish, so long as
you give them the same freedoms you received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A prototype can be built from these pieces in around 20 hours of
development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are Bermudians with the skills to do this and the time to devote
to such a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases they will be exploring new concepts, but that is the
nature of IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many others they can call on to assist should they need
guidance, including the millions of people around the globe who
contribute to free software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="accessibility"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility is often neglected in software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many free software tools have good support for accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, a framework is provided to address a wide range of
accessibility issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has different challenges working with computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hearing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;motor movements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;speech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;language processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;writing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the software itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;citizens access to information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bermuda is an international island.  English is the dominant
language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documents are generally produced in English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the island has many nationalities living here and also has
many Bermudians who have travelled and lived abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also distinct communities within Bermuda with their own
language, culture and history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, of course, Bermuda is a popular travel destination, with many
nationalities paying visits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet there is very poor support for languages other than English on
most Bermuda related websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A free software solution would accommodate translations.  Further, it
would allow anyone to contribute to those translations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free software: means you can adapt for differing needs, since you have
the code.  Without the code you are tied to a third party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further others can help you.  A free software census solution for
Bermuda may be usable in many other juristictions.  Bermudians who
develop such software would be able to work with others wherever in
the world they may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="public-access-to-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Public Access To Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Census data is invaluable in many ways.  It provides data that can
guide public policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO: Anology: vaccination: having your children vaccinated protects
them against illness, but also reduces the chance of epidemics
breaking out.  There are small risks to every vaccination, but the
benefits to society can be significant.  For example, consider the
elimination of polio, a disease that affect large numbers of people in
the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the UK there have been censuses since 1831 (may have been earlier).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collecting the data back in that day was a huge task.  At the time it
gave vast amounts of information about poplulation sizes, household
sizes and the age profile of the population and their occupations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the data was hand written.  Pages of data might have totals and
there were presumably clerks creating aggregate statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, genealogists find the census data both fascinating and
invaluable as they trace family history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has been digitising this data over the last few years and
making it available on line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A free software solution to the census would anticipate PATI requests
by building access to information into the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than wait for PATI requests and have to then examine data to
see what should be released, the decisions about what should be
released, when and to who will be made up front and built into the
solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A system can be built that will only release certain information after
some specified period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some data may need reviewing after some number of years and released
or re-sealed based on that review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="transparency-and-privacy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transparency and Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is assumed that aggregate data from the census will be made freely
available to citizens.  Our solution will include support for such
access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is recommended that any data of a sensitive nature be treated
appropriately, including the physical security of any computers
storing the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possibility is to try to build a system that only stores
aggregrate information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should also be noted that in a small community like Bermuda
aggregate data, especially when combined with other similar data can
remove annonynimity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One recommendation would be to encourage community discussion about
the census questions and have the community guide the decisions
regarding privacy and access to information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collecting more personal data that will be stored in some sort of time
capsule for the benefit of future historians and genealogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="computer-insecurity"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Computer insecurity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In view of all the high profile data breaches that the world has been
experiencing over recent months it should be apparent that storing
sensitive data on computers is not an easy task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our solution will recognise this fact and propose appropriate measures
for storing more sensitive data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it would be our recommendation to only collect data that the
residents of Bermuda are comfortable in sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="maintenance-and-development"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Maintenance and Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a free software solution future maintenance and development of
the software can be performed by anyone with the skills.  The local
poplulation will have all the tools they need, they just need to learn
the skills needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, a well designed free software census would be usable in other
jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If developed here in Bermuda by Bermudians it would create
opportunities for the team to work elsewhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="free-software-centre"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Free Software Centre&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ownership-of-code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ownership of code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government, not the developers would own and code developed for
the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted most of the code already exists and is free
software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is suggested that any code written for the project be itself
released as a free software project using the GPL license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="existing-free-software-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Existing Free Software solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.census.gov/data/software.html"&gt;http://www.census.gov/data/software.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="appendix-a-python-and-django"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Appendix A: Python and Django&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="django"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Django&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="django-quiz"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Django Quiz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="appendix-project-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Appendix:  Project Jupyter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans in different parts of the world speak different languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans have also developed many different languages for communicating
with computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning these languages can take considerable time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of the history of modern computing, communicating with other
languages has been difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In effect, the plethora of languages has worked to Balkanise the IT
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Project Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; is just one project that is helping languages work
together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jupyter is a tool that supports virtually seamless interoperability
between 50 different languages, from python, to perl, C++ to C#, Bash
to Brainfuck, erlang to lua, matlab to php.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="choosing-tools"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Choosing tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers invariably like to use the tools they know best.  They
understand them, know what they are capable of and know many of the
risks they will encounter using those tools to solve a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a project with a new tool presents many additional risks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;will it work as advertised?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time will it take to learn?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an organisation starting out in the free software world the choice
can be daunting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, any large organisation will likely end up using many
different languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst there are inefficiencies in this approach, there are
advantages, just as with growing crops: monoculture leaves an
organisation vulnerable to anything which threatens that ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Variety gives resilience, but at some cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects such as Jupyter help support that variety and reduce the
costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a particular technology choice is proving hard to support, porting
to another Jupyter supported language is always an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- title: links --&gt;
&lt;!-- slug: references --&gt;
&lt;!-- date: 2014-11-13 14:08:31 UTC --&gt;
&lt;!-- tags: --&gt;
&lt;!-- link: --&gt;
&lt;!-- description: links to include in all posts --&gt;
&lt;!-- type: text --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bermuda</category><category>census</category><category>free software</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/census-survey.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 15:07:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fred Update</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/fred-update.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fred formed way in the east of the Atlantic.  I believe it was already
a hurricane going over the Cape Verde islands.  I was shown pictures
today of seas damaging a pier.  I have not heard too much more about
damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six years ago, Fred formed around the same area a little further
south, but did not intensify as fast.  It did become a hurricane, then
dissipated as it curled, for a short while was heading easterly, then
got pushed back westward.  By this time it had fallen apart and it
did not get organised again, but the remnants of the storm tracked a
good way across the Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the discussion of Fred, it is likely to be pulled apart in
the short term.  Then the track forecasts give a range of
possibilities, including heading westward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Latest (5AM AST, 1st September) forecast discussion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nhc.noaa.gov/text/refresh/MIATCDAT1+shtml/010849.shtml"&gt;http://www.nhc.noaa.gov/text/refresh/MIATCDAT1+shtml/010849.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These discussions tend to be very helpful in gauging how much
confidence the forecasters about the forecasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, both track and intensity forecasts can be pretty accurate
out to 24 hours or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paragraph from the discussion has a lot of information in it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Fred is expected to move between west-northwest and northwest for
the next 72 hours as a mid-level ridge to the north of the cyclone
gradually builds westward. After that time, a turn toward the
north-northwest and north is forecast due to a deep-layer trough
currently over eastern Canada that is expected to dig
southeastward over the central Atlantic and erode the ridge. The
NHC model guidance is in decent agreement on this developing
pattern change.  However, there are significant differences in the
model solutions with the HWRF, GFS, and GFDL models keeping Fred
stronger and making the northward turn sooner, whereas the weaker
solution models like the UKMET and ECMWF take a weaker and more
vertically shallow cyclone farther west before turning it
northward.  The official forecast track is a little south of the
previous advisory track, mainly due to the more southerly initial
position, and follows a blend of the weaker UKMET and ECMWF
solutions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end, we learn the current forecast track is further south than
the previous advisory.  The discussion notes this is mostly because
Fred did not move as far north as expected over the previous period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disagreements in models are usually informative, often indicating
there is more uncertainty in the forecast.  Sometimes the forecasters
have good understanding of why the models are disagreeing, different
models have different strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bermuda-weather"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bermuda Weather&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://weather.bm/images/surfaceAnalysis/Latest/Atlantic.gif"&gt;http://weather.bm/images/surfaceAnalysis/Latest/Atlantic.gif&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="wikipedia"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Fred_%282015%29"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Fred_%282015%29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Fred_%282009%29"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Fred_%282009%29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="national-hurricane-centre"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;National Hurricane Centre&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://weather.bm/images/surfaceAnalysis/Latest/Atlantic.gif"&gt;http://weather.bm/images/surfaceAnalysis/Latest/Atlantic.gif&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>2014</category><category>2015</category><category>fred</category><category>hurricane</category><category>weather</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/fred-update.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:41:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Erika, Andrew, Danny and Fred</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/erika-andrew-danny-and-fred.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last few weeks the Atlantic hurricane season has got more active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danny never really got started, was blown apart by sheer, but no doubt
spawned a lot of thunderstorms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flooding from Erika has resulted in numerous deaths in Domincan
Republic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erika has fallen apart, but again there will be a lot of thunderstorms
along its path.  There is a lot of moisture in the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="erika"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Erika&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early forecasts had the most likely track heading over Hispanola, Then
curving, but likely being blown apart by sheer from strong upper
atmosphere winds related to El Nino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is in fact very close to what actually has happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="track-forecast"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Track forecast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather models started to suggest the storm would curve more
northerly.  This all involves really complex systems that stretch over
thousands of miles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the models most likely path was more northerly, and that might take
it on a path to hit Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point the most likely track was heading all up the east coast
of Florida, without making landfall.  If it had held together it might
of intensified over hot water with low windsheer and been a major
storm at landfall in the Carolinas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this period there was always the possibility of heading
over Hispanola, but it wasn't the most likely path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="andrew"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Andrew&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew formed in a similar season to 2015 with a high El Nino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took a more northerly track, steered north of the Caribbean, then
turned straight into Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a comparison of Andrew and Erika, Danny too, would be
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="fred"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fred&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hurricane names run on a six year cycle.  So, there are six lists,
that repeat every six years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a storm becomes significant in some way, usually the more intense
and damaging storms that hit land, the name gets &lt;em&gt;retired&lt;/em&gt; from the
list and is forever associated with that storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we have Fred.  Now for me, Fred means Fiery Fred Trueman,
Yorkshire and England fast bolwer.  I never saw him play, but often
heard him commentating on test matches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So some day we will see a Fiery Fred storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A storm named Fred has just formed.  Like Erika, there is a fair
amount of uncertainty on what path it takes and how intense it will
get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="more-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Johnston has also been blogging about the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bermudaweather.wordpress.com/2015/08/30/active-tropics/"&gt;recent storms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hurricane</category><category>weather</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/erika-andrew-danny-and-fred.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2015 21:39:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The raspberry pi super computer</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/the-raspberry-pi-super-computer.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The raspberry pi 2 comes with around 6 times the processing power of
the original pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is still fairly low powered, but it is interesting to compare the
pi with some older computers that were considered powerful in their
day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pi comes with an ARM 7, quad-core processor.  It also has a
Broadcom graphics processor that can potentially be used for compute
intensive work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also comes with 1GB of memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For disk storage the nornal approach is to use a micro SD card.  There
are 16GB cards that give 45MB/s read/write capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For less than $1000 you can get 20 pi's, with fast SD cards.  The
result is a machine with 80 cores, 16GB of memory and 320GB of disk,
with a combined bandwidth of 900MB/s read and write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These things are low power, so a 20 pi machine would require just 100
watts of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is reasonable to assume that more powerful devices will be
available in he future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, computing power is becoming very, very cheap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="cray-xmp"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cray-XMP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give some indication of how cheap compute power has become, this
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://vk5tu.livejournal.com/50955.html"&gt;comparison to a Cray-XMP&lt;/a&gt; shows that the older Pi B+ has very
similar compute power to the Cray-XMP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you compate the inflation adjusted price tags you see how cheap
compute power has become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pi 2 is roughly six times the power of the B+.  Hence 20 of those
gives you 120 Cray-XMP's.   For $1000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="renewable-energy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Renewable energy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One criticism often directed at renewable energy is that sun, wind and
wave are not reliable.  In order to reliably meet peak demand much
it is necessary to have much more capacity than is needed on average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to mitigate this cost is to have uses for the spare capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possible use is to have a compute farm to mop up spare capacity.
This works particularly well if you have long running computations
that can be used to mop up spare compute cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin mining is one potential application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Cray</category><category>Cray-XMP</category><category>raspberry pi</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/the-raspberry-pi-super-computer.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 22:08:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Red and White v Blue and White</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/red-and-white-v-blue-and-white.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday there was a big cricket match at Lord's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not the Lord's where England were falling apart as the Aussies were
dominating the second test, but Lord's in St David's, Bermuda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bailey's Bay were playing Cleveland County in what is known as the
Eastern Counties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each team in Bermuda has its colours, Bay are red and white, Cleveland
are blue and white.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I come from Sheffield, UK, a city divided between the blue and white
of the Owls and the red and white of the Mighty Blades.  I follow the
Blades, so it was natural for me to be cheering for Bailey's Bay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a slow start to the day and it was a long (for Bermuda) ride on
the moped to St David's, so we didn't get to the ground until just
before lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we entered we were greeted by a larger than life character in red
and white.  Once I took out my red and white, &lt;em&gt;cat in the hat&lt;/em&gt;
headgear he directed us towards the Digicel tent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_123538.jpg" src="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_123538.jpg" style="width: 400px; height: 300px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game was nicely poised, with Cleveland batting first and on about
80 runs for 4 wickets at lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch the Bay bowlers dominated and Cleveland were bowled out
for 127 in 49.3 overs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_151601.jpg" src="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_151601.jpg" style="width: 400px; height: 300px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lord's is a wonderful ground, right by the ocean, with natural banks
on which people build stands.  Between innings we went for a walk
round the ground and took some pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_125203.jpg" src="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_125203.jpg" style="width: 400px; height: 300px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there is the precariously perched commentary position that
you have to walk the plank to get to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_152446.jpg" src="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_152446.jpg" style="width: 400px; height: 300px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now being a Blades supporter I have got used to my team snatching
defeat from the jaws of victory.  The target of 128 that Bay were set
should have been easily within their grasp, but we were about to
witness one of the most bizarre afternoon's cricket there ever was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bay lost two early wickets, but then regrouped and the batsmen were
starting to open up at 50-2.   Cleveland had a couple of strong
appeals turned down.  There was a strong appeal for a catch, but it
was one of those where it was hard to tell if the ball had been
blocked into the ground or hit the ground and come off the bat.  The
umpire gave the benefit of the doubt to the batsman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleveland protested and for 40 minutes chaos ensued.  Both coaches,
the president of the Eastern Counties and even a policeman took to the
pitch to try and get the game restarted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_171958.jpg" src="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/galleries/EasternCounties/20150718_171958.jpg" style="width: 400px; height: 300px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after the restart, there was another delay for a drinks break.
The batsmen were finding it difficult to get into any sort of rhythm
and first ball after the break a wicket fell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this wickets fell steadily, but Bay always looked like they
would make it.  Until, after 30 overs, with the scores tied and Bay
with just 2 wickets remaining the umpires declared the game over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the scores tied, Cleveland, as holders, were declared winners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It reminded me of the infamous F.A. Cup tie when the Blades were
holding their own against an Arsenal side.  The ball was kicked into
play for an injury.  The resulting throw was sportingly thrown back to
the blades players, but Kanu did not seem to understand what was
happening, raced onto the ball and slotted it into the net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arsenal went on to win, but Wenger graciously agreed to replay the
game.  Of course, the Blades went on to lose the replay, but at least
the game was not decided by this bizarre incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read today that the Cleveland coach was very unhappy with his sides
behaviour, perhaps he will follow Wenger's example and ask for the
game to be replayed.  However, that might not be possible given the
busy summer cricket schedule here in Bermuda, with Cup Match &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/red-and-white-v-blue-and-white.html#id2" id="id1"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; less than
two weeks away this might not be an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's Royal Gazette has a full page &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.royalgazette.com/article/20150720/COMMENT01/150729969"&gt;editorial&lt;/a&gt; on the game.  There
are also rumours that Cleveland have been &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.royalgazette.com/article/20150720/SPORT02/150729960"&gt;stripped of the cup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is never dull following the Red and White wizards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for the cricket, the day itself was fun from beginning to
end.  Unfortunately, I had packed the bag of stuff to take to the
ground, so instead of drinks and food and sunscreen we had an
assortment of raspberry pi's, humidity sensors, air pressure sensors,
wires, breadboards and a netbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was food in the clubhouse, yellow and blue, St David's colours.
So we were able to find some chips that weren't made of silicon.  And
the rum swizzle went down very smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The banter in the crowd rarely stopped, with fans from both sides
sitting enjoying together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cricket in Bermuda is very much something you go to watch with family
and friends.  Worst case, you have a day in the sunshine in a
beautiful setting, with people you love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next stop the blue and red of Somerset playing the light and dark blue
of St George's.  Cup Match!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id2" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/red-and-white-v-blue-and-white.html#id1"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cup match is a two day game between the Red and Blue of
Somerset and the dark and light blue of St Georges.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/red-and-white-v-blue-and-white.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 00:35:52 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>