<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Around the world in 80 days (communication)</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/categories/communication.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2016 20:10:08 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Perspective, Communication, Stress and the Stack</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/perspective-communication-stress-and-the-stack.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many years ago there was a programme on the BBC, I can't remember the
name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groups of high school pupils would present a science project they were
working on.  I think each programme would cover 2-3 schools and there
were also follow-ups on projects to see how they were progressing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were all sorts of fascinating things being done.  A lot of
chemistry experiments, physics, biology too.  And there was always a
teacher in the background who was inspiring these young people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recall one show, where a team was investigating stress.  The panel
were very much pure scientists.   One commented"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
"nobody really knows how to define stress".&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stuck with me.  It was weird, because pretty much everyone I knew
had expeienced stress.  There wasn't really a good definition,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The panel were focussed on the fact the team did not really have a
clear definition of what they were trying to study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stress is everywhere, but it is different for everyone.  Each has
their own perspective, interests, concerns and fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focussing on the causes of stress it is easy to miss what the essence
of the stress feeling is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a personal perspective, but I suspect many will recognise some
of what follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the number of things I care about and feel the need to act on
increases, so the stress builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="computers-and-being-able-to-fix-them"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Computers and being able to fix them&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like fixing things and making things.  When you have some pieces you
can put together and test an idea, make something work a little
better, a little easier then I find that satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, each fix uncovers other problems you did not know
existed.  You find new ideas to pursue, the list of things you care
about grows.  You find fascinating new ideas, that mesh with other
things you care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you work with computers and use modern software tools so many
things can be improved.  And each improvement is a small step in a
good direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="rabbit-holes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rabbit holes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, the simple task can turn into many other simple tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And meanwhile you encounter new brokenness and want to fix that too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to get dragged into rabbit holes, forgetting what you were
originally trying to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="burnout"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Burnout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the stack gets too deep then you have stress.  Too many things to
think about and no time for any of them.  More things arriving faster
than you can even process them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="control"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Control&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be many things you have no control over, but that are
important to you and things you care about.  You need help from
others, but they have their own perspective, their own stack of
nightmares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="stress-is-not-all-bad"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stress is not all bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can reduce the stress, get some breathing space, then you have
a stack of interesting things to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="unwinding-the-stack"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unwinding the stack&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you unwind the stack, look for patterns, group items.   Look for
solutions that address many issue not just one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for bridges to build and look for others at the other side of the
ravine who can help you cross and share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prune the stack, discard what is not relevant now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask if the things that you cannot control matter?  If they do, how can
you get help?   Who else cares about this?  Why do you care?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>communication</category><category>perspective</category><category>stack</category><category>stress</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/perspective-communication-stress-and-the-stack.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 21:15:10 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>