<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Around the world in 80 days (hills)</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/categories/hills.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 17:34:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Mountains, Valleys and Bridges</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/mountains-valleys-and-bridges.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="hill-climbing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hill Climbing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up close to the hills of the Peak District in Derbyshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highest point of the Peak District is the summit of Kinder Scout.
This is also the first hill along the Pennine Way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most times I have climbed it via Grindsbrook.  It is steep in places
and follows alongside a small river and stream.  This used to be the
Pennine Way route, but now the official route takes you up the
gentler, but no less strenuous, Jacob's Ladder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not even sure if I have ever made it to the highest point on
Kinder Scout.  The summit is more of a plateau, a strange landscape of
tiny streams running along little valleys cut into the peat the covers
the summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most times I have been there it has been covered in cloud, navigating
with the help of a compass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on a clear day you can walk to the spectacular Kinder Downfall and
see all the way to Manchester and even beyond to the mountains of
Snowdonia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the UK, hills become mountains if they are 3000 feet or higher.
Snowdonia has mountains, the Peak District has hills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="false-summits"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;False summits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some hills I have climbed tease you with false summits.   You think
you are nearing the top, and then as you clamber over rocks, behind
what you thought was the summit, the route continues, onward and
upward.  Some hills have many false summits, each more enticing than
the last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="summits"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reaching a summit is always a highlight.  Stood on the highest point
in the area and, weather permitting there will be uninterrupted views
all around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="following-a-ridge"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Following a Ridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having toiled to climb a hill you will rightly be satisfied with the
view you have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when you look across the land there is a spectactular
hill, dwarfing the one you have just climbed.  You can only imagine
how the view might look from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often the new summit is easily accessible from where you are, by
following a ridge that connects to the peak you have just climbed.  A
small descent and a longer climb may be all that is needed to reach a
new high-point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ridge acts like a natural bridge between two summits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bridging-the-valley"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bridging the valley&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes there is no such bridge.  Curiosity might drive you to
attempt the larger peak in the distance, but descending into the
valley after all that hard work climbing, just to climb another hill,
can be a daunting task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be a river in the valley bottom, difficult to cross and
requiring a detour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bridges across valleys connect those either side.  They can be
difficult to build.  Without people either side willing to work
together it may not be possible to cross the divide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crossing a new bridge requires courage too.  There are rope walkways
across plunging gorges that I for one do not have the courage to
cross, let alone be the first to try out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first across are generally the bridge builders, often crossing
before the bridge is complete, fixing it along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Millennium Bridge across the Thames in London.  When people
started to walk across the bridge, the rhythm of their steps caused it
to resonate and wobble.  It was closed for months for modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soldiers always break out of step when marching across a bridge, for a
similar reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who build bridges have courage and vision, leading the way to a
new mountain with a more spectacular view, or uniting communities
previously separated by a plunging ravine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="going-the-long-way-round"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Going the long way round&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often there is no bridge, the valley may be too wide or deep, or just
not enough people wanting to cross to justify a high-level crossing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you can rest at the summit, admire the view and be content with
your achievements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you may be intrigued by the mountain you have seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Descending into the valley you may get that sinking feeling, as you
lose all that height that took so much work to gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The valley bottom may have a bubbling river where you can drink,
perhaps catch a fish and regroup for the climb ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once, refreshed the long climb starts.  As you climb you can gauge
progress by looking across to the hill on which you once stood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point you will draw level with the summit and once again be
able to see the view beyond the hill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be daunted, recalling how much taller this mountain is, how
much more you have to climb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But every step takes you higher than you were before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bridges</category><category>hill climbing</category><category>hills</category><category>mountains</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/mountains-valleys-and-bridges.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 12:33:26 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>