<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Around the world in 80 days (weather)</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/categories/weather.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2016 20:10:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Raspberry Pi Sense Hat</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/raspberry-pi-sense-hat.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just discovered the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/products/sense-hat/"&gt;raspberry pi sense hat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking about putting together raspberry pi's, sensors
and mopeds to make a mobile weather station and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in Bermuda we have mopeds.  Power supplies are one thing that is
causing me some thinking with pi's.  They only need about 5 watts of
power.  With the pizero, I think it is about 1-2 watts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar is always an option, but then the sun goes in.  There is wind
and rain too.  Lots of ways to get enough power.  And batteries to
store for when there is nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, mopeds have batteries.  They also have this thing that
sits between your legs and creates explosions lots of times per
second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sense-hat"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sense Hat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/products/sense-hat/"&gt;https://www.raspberrypi.org/products/sense-hat/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have spend all of five minutes looking at this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has sensors for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gyroscope&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accelerometer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Magnetometer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temperature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Barometric pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humidity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it has a mini joystick as well as an 8x8 matrix display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It plugs neatly into a pi 2's and I expect could be adapted to the
pizero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and it is being used for the Astro pi project on the international
space station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://astro-pi.org/"&gt;https://astro-pi.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am thinking of adding a wifi chip and a GPS chip.  The latter is
also good for a real time clock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sense had also comes with a python library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pythonhosted.org/sense-hat/"&gt;http://pythonhosted.org/sense-hat/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are all sorts of other tools that look useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't find it now, but I saw another sense hat piece of code that
was storing readings in a python flask app, which is what I have been
trying to do with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/peakrisk/sunshine"&gt;sunshine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, all I need now is one of those Apollo helmets for the moped, with
the gold coated visor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>pycaribbean</category><category>python</category><category>raspberry pi</category><category>weather</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/raspberry-pi-sense-hat.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2016 00:13:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hurricane Joaquin</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/hurricane-joaquin.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hurricane Joaquim is now category 4 and expected to strengthen some
more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been over the Bahamas for a long time now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bermudaweather.wordpress.com/"&gt;Michael Johnston&lt;/a&gt;'s weather blog is a wonderful, Bermuda centric
weather blog and a good resource to check for those in Bermuda
wondering if Joaquin is heading this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael is currently studying meteorology at Penn State.  He worked at
the Bermuda weather service this summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="uncertainty-in-paths"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Uncertainty in paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been consdierable disagreement across models over what track
this storm will take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather systems are complex at present.  The models are coming
into better agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In situations like this it would be very useful to have more
information on the likely intensity given each path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Hurricane Centre discussion is always helpful.  It feels
like the forecasts are getting better at getting the intensity right,
given the right track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track tends to be driven by larger systems whose interaction is
hard to predict.  But often, given the direction the hurricane travels
we can learn a bit about how those systems will evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that open and free software combined, with open scientific
collaboration, can help communities better prepare for these events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="direction-of-change-in-model-predictions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Direction of change in model predictions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way the model predictions move can be informative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the models may have been leaning more in that direction, all of
them would likely have assigned some probability to the general
direcion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seems to be some inertia in the models, so sometimes as they
shift the direction of the forecast, the next update also moves a
little in that direction: when the forecasts are changing, more change
is often more likely, it indicates that the driving features are
changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="climate-change"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Climate Change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it indicates there is a new factor in play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate change is increasing occurrences of unusual weather.  Regions
are experiencing conditions at the extremes of what they have
experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases these are conditions that the region is poorly adapted
to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The models will also be experiencing conditions outside the area where
they have been callibrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will provide good data and new insigts to improve them for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bermuda"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bermuda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first anniversary of Fay and Gonzalo is fast approaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now Joaquin is moving very slowly, battering Caribbean islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest forecasts have it well west of Bermuda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track should become more certain over then next 24 hours or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Latest 11,00pm EDT October 1, 2015 discussion has this paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The forecast models continue to indicate a track farther away
from the United States east coast and the threat of direct impacts
from Joaquin in the Carolinas and mid-Atlantic states appears to be
decreasing.  However, the threat of impacts in Bermuda has increased
and a Tropical Storm or Hurricane Watch could be required for that
island on Friday.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be good to have more info on the likely intensity should it
take a path close to Bermuda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There still appears to be a fair bit of uncertainty about the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hurricane</category><category>Joaquin</category><category>weather</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/hurricane-joaquin.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 02:18:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fred Update</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/fred-update.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fred formed way in the east of the Atlantic.  I believe it was already
a hurricane going over the Cape Verde islands.  I was shown pictures
today of seas damaging a pier.  I have not heard too much more about
damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six years ago, Fred formed around the same area a little further
south, but did not intensify as fast.  It did become a hurricane, then
dissipated as it curled, for a short while was heading easterly, then
got pushed back westward.  By this time it had fallen apart and it
did not get organised again, but the remnants of the storm tracked a
good way across the Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the discussion of Fred, it is likely to be pulled apart in
the short term.  Then the track forecasts give a range of
possibilities, including heading westward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Latest (5AM AST, 1st September) forecast discussion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nhc.noaa.gov/text/refresh/MIATCDAT1+shtml/010849.shtml"&gt;http://www.nhc.noaa.gov/text/refresh/MIATCDAT1+shtml/010849.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These discussions tend to be very helpful in gauging how much
confidence the forecasters about the forecasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, both track and intensity forecasts can be pretty accurate
out to 24 hours or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paragraph from the discussion has a lot of information in it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Fred is expected to move between west-northwest and northwest for
the next 72 hours as a mid-level ridge to the north of the cyclone
gradually builds westward. After that time, a turn toward the
north-northwest and north is forecast due to a deep-layer trough
currently over eastern Canada that is expected to dig
southeastward over the central Atlantic and erode the ridge. The
NHC model guidance is in decent agreement on this developing
pattern change.  However, there are significant differences in the
model solutions with the HWRF, GFS, and GFDL models keeping Fred
stronger and making the northward turn sooner, whereas the weaker
solution models like the UKMET and ECMWF take a weaker and more
vertically shallow cyclone farther west before turning it
northward.  The official forecast track is a little south of the
previous advisory track, mainly due to the more southerly initial
position, and follows a blend of the weaker UKMET and ECMWF
solutions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end, we learn the current forecast track is further south than
the previous advisory.  The discussion notes this is mostly because
Fred did not move as far north as expected over the previous period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disagreements in models are usually informative, often indicating
there is more uncertainty in the forecast.  Sometimes the forecasters
have good understanding of why the models are disagreeing, different
models have different strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bermuda-weather"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bermuda Weather&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://weather.bm/images/surfaceAnalysis/Latest/Atlantic.gif"&gt;http://weather.bm/images/surfaceAnalysis/Latest/Atlantic.gif&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="wikipedia"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Fred_%282015%29"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Fred_%282015%29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Fred_%282009%29"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Fred_%282009%29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="national-hurricane-centre"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;National Hurricane Centre&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://weather.bm/images/surfaceAnalysis/Latest/Atlantic.gif"&gt;http://weather.bm/images/surfaceAnalysis/Latest/Atlantic.gif&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>2014</category><category>2015</category><category>fred</category><category>hurricane</category><category>weather</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/fred-update.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:41:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Erika, Andrew, Danny and Fred</title><link>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/erika-andrew-danny-and-fred.html</link><dc:creator>Johnny Gill</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last few weeks the Atlantic hurricane season has got more active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danny never really got started, was blown apart by sheer, but no doubt
spawned a lot of thunderstorms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flooding from Erika has resulted in numerous deaths in Domincan
Republic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erika has fallen apart, but again there will be a lot of thunderstorms
along its path.  There is a lot of moisture in the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="erika"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Erika&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early forecasts had the most likely track heading over Hispanola, Then
curving, but likely being blown apart by sheer from strong upper
atmosphere winds related to El Nino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is in fact very close to what actually has happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="track-forecast"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Track forecast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather models started to suggest the storm would curve more
northerly.  This all involves really complex systems that stretch over
thousands of miles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the models most likely path was more northerly, and that might take
it on a path to hit Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point the most likely track was heading all up the east coast
of Florida, without making landfall.  If it had held together it might
of intensified over hot water with low windsheer and been a major
storm at landfall in the Carolinas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this period there was always the possibility of heading
over Hispanola, but it wasn't the most likely path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="andrew"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Andrew&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew formed in a similar season to 2015 with a high El Nino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took a more northerly track, steered north of the Caribbean, then
turned straight into Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a comparison of Andrew and Erika, Danny too, would be
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="fred"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fred&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hurricane names run on a six year cycle.  So, there are six lists,
that repeat every six years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a storm becomes significant in some way, usually the more intense
and damaging storms that hit land, the name gets &lt;em&gt;retired&lt;/em&gt; from the
list and is forever associated with that storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we have Fred.  Now for me, Fred means Fiery Fred Trueman,
Yorkshire and England fast bolwer.  I never saw him play, but often
heard him commentating on test matches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So some day we will see a Fiery Fred storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A storm named Fred has just formed.  Like Erika, there is a fair
amount of uncertainty on what path it takes and how intense it will
get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="more-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Johnston has also been blogging about the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bermudaweather.wordpress.com/2015/08/30/active-tropics/"&gt;recent storms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hurricane</category><category>weather</category><guid>http://openbermuda.github.io/80days/posts/erika-andrew-danny-and-fred.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2015 21:39:48 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>